PROFILE

A technical architect with an insatiable passion for learning, always on the lookout for emerging technologies with which to dabble. With more than 15 years of professional experience in software design and development, I have vast experience and knowledge in creating and implementing technological solutions while leading teams of developers in the realization of every project. I not only oversee project development to ensure proper architecture is implemented but also get down to the nitty gritty of hands-on development because it is what I love to do.

CONTACT

PHONE: +1 415-528-3672 / +639175786869 WEBSITE: https://github.com/artotoy EMAIL: arthur.olano@gmail.com

CERTIFICATIONS

Amazon Web Services Solutions Architect Associate

Date Taken: 2021-08-05

Sun Certified Web Component Developer (SCWCD)

Date Taken: 2007-02-23

Sun Certified Java Programmer (SCJP)

Date Taken: 2004-12-01

AWARD

Winner of 5-day Silicon Valley Trip (All Expense Paid) - California, USA

Contest: Top 15 SME Companies for Mobile

Readiness

Mobile Apps: Olryt Homes Philippines

Date: October 2015

HACKATONS

FIS InnovateOn 2021

Project Submitted: Project I.C.E. Technology Used: S3, AWS Lambda, EC2, DynamoDB, Python, Angular6, EC2, Serverless Framework, Terraform Date: Sept 2021

FIS InnovateIN48 2020

Project Submitted: Sheldon Project

ARTHUR OLANO

SOFTWARE ARCHITECT, LEAD & DEVELOPER

Preferred Work Type: Regular/Contractual | Fully Remote

WORK EXPERIENCE

ING Bank Philippines [Jan 2022 – Present]

Senior Engineer IV

- Served as scrum master on daily scrums
- Designed application architecture from scratch
- Attended technical trainings from experts

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

- Leadership and communication skills
- Java 8, Springboot, Merak, Baker, Bakery, Azure DevOps, Gitlab

FIS Global [Feb 2018 – Dec 2021]

Technical Lead

Served as a technical lead, led teams of developers from inception to delivery of a project.

- Served as SME and technical liaison between developers and business partners
- Conducted POC for architecture validation
- Designed web application from scratch
- Designed brand-new database
- Active participation in code development
- Implemented CI/CD using Github actions and deployment to Azure platform
- Provided technical guidance and coaching to developers, conducted code reviews
- Implemented ETL process
- Conducted technical interviews to new applicants
- Prepared daily, weekly, monthly, and annual reports

Project: Sheldon Project (Sept 2018 – Present)

Employee monitoring system that track employee activities and monitor worker engagement with workplace related tasks.

Project: AllProfits (Feb 2018 – Present)

A banking system that handles Loans, Deposits, Trade, Finance, and Remittances.

Project: Asia Support Center (Feb 2020 – Present)

A support team that handles Asia-Pacific region client with issues on AllProfits, Profiles and Systematic banking system.

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

Technology Used: Java8, Angular6,

Springboot Date: June 2020

FIS InnovateIN48 2019

Project Submitted: FIS Coin Technology Used: Blockhain, Java8

Date: May 2019

TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

Languages – Java 8, Android SDK, PL/SQL, C/C++, PHP, Ruby, SQL, XHTML5, CSS, JavaScript, Laszlo, Freemarker, Velocity, Adobe FLEX

Frameworks – Springboot, SpringMVC, Stripes, Ruby Rails, CakePHP, Flex Cairngorm, Oracle Application Framework (OAF)

Web Service – REST API, XFire, Axis Cloud – Azure, Amazon Web Services (AWS) Front End Scripting – Angular 6, Angular JS, EXTJS Sencha, JQuery Mobile, Bootstrap Persistence/ORM Frameworks – Spring JPA, Hibernate, Castor JDO

Technologies/Libraries – Android SDK, JSP, Servlets, Swing, Dom4J, JDBC, RMI, AJAX, JAXP, Castor Mapping, JavaComm, Sockets, Threads, JavaMail, JNI, Maven, Ant, Junit

Database – DynamoDB, Oracle, SQLServer, MySQL, DB2

Operating Systems – Ubuntu, Gentoo, Knoppix, Solaris, Windows

Social Apps Scripting – Google Play Services, Google Apps SDK, Facebook Apps SDK

DevOps Tools – Kubernetes, Docker, CircleCl, ArgoCD, ArgoWorkflow, Lens **Test Tools** – Postman, SoapUl **Versioning Tool** – Git, SVN, CVS, Clearcase

EDUCATION

Ateneo de Naga University

1998 – 2003

BS Electronics and Communications Engineering

- Leadership and project management skills
- Java 8, Springboot, Angular, Bootstrap, NodeJS, S3, AWS Lambda, EC2, DynamoDB, Spring Data JPA, Azure, Github CI/CD, MySQL, REST API, Server Sent Events (SSE), Cron Jobs, JIRA, MSSQL
- User requirement gathering and documentation, Database Design Documentation, Functional Design Documentation, Use Case Documentation

Nova Solutions [April 2016 – Jan 2018]

Technical Lead

Lead a team of developers in maintenance and enhancement of multiple projects

- Gathered user requirements with users
- Reverse engineered an existing project
- Designed the screens, business logic, and code architecture of the portal
- Developed form submissions, validations, webservices, and 3D secure online payment portal
- Tested the project in SIT and UAT environment, while coordinating directly with the users
- Supported the users on PROD environment and fixed production issues
- Led a team of 4, provided guidance and delegated tasks
- Conducted training for new team members on current production system and technologies

Project: Mobile Portal for Legal Cases (April 2016 – Feb 2017) A LAB e-services portal for public for legal cases application.

Project: ISPS 2 (Feb 2017 – Aug 2017) Building and construction permits and application forms submissions

Project: URA DAX (Aug 2017 – Jan 2018)

Development application, enforcement, legal requisition development charge and fees/refund/transfer processing for urban redevelopment and land use planning

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

- Leadership Skills, Management Skills
- EXTJS Sencha, Spring, Struts2, Java SDK, JSON, Restful Webservices, SQLServer, Hibernate, Visio, Pencil
- User requirement gathering and documentation, Database Design Documentation, Functional Design Documentation, Use Case Documentation

Olryt Marketing & Management [Feb 2012 – April 2016]

IT Manager/Developer, Real Estate Broker

Acted as a real estate broker as well as designed, developed, and maintained both web and mobile applications

- Lead a team of brokers and salespeople
- Developed an android app project for real estate

- Developed a real estate management system from scratch up to production stage
- Provided software solutions and modules for real estate agents
- Trained users, testers, and developers
- Conducted training to developers, brokers, and agents
- Maintained android apps and websites

Project: Real Estate Management System (Feb 2012 – April 2016) A system for monitoring sales & commissions, accounting, project inventories, and directory of brokers, agents, project developers, and coordinators

Project: Olryt Homes Philippines (Sept 2014 – Dec 2014) An android mobile app for project inventories and developer's access for real estate brokers and agents

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

- Leadership, sale and negotiating, and marketing skills
- Android SDK, Android Studio, Java, PHP, SQL, Google Play Services, iMacros

Asian Development Bank [December 2007 – February 2012] Sr. Java/J2EE System Analyst

A senior consultant responsible for project development of feature enhancements, testing and deployment.

- Developed automated unit and performance testing
- Developed business intelligent reports
- Deployed and maintained releases of the project

Project: Project Processing and Portfolio Management(P3M)A system used for managing loan/grant assisted government projects

Project: Operational Data Source (ODS)

A system used for displaying, analyzing and evaluating all the reports for loand and technical assistance projects

Project: Clean Energy and Environment Database System (CEEDS)A system used for identifying and tracking clean energy investment projects

Acquired Skills/Tools Used:

 J2EE, Oracle Application Framework (OAF), Ant, Toad, Oracle DB, Jdeveloper, IBM Cognos, Spring MVC, Junit, Tomcat, UML, IBM Rational ClearCase

Black Marlin Data Corporation [June 2007 – November 2007] Sr Java/J2EE Consultant & Technical Lead

A technical lead and senior consultant responsible for redesigning project architecture, design documentation, project development, testing and deployment.

- Developed automated testing tools and documentation
- Deployed and maintained releases of the project

Lead a team of 3 developers

Project: CMR Integrator

A middle tier project that processes shipment invoices

Project: PC*Miler Interface for Accuship

A middle tier application that compute cost and mileage for a trip

Acquired Skills/Tools Used:

 J2EE, Spring Framework, Linux, Junit, Visio, Eclipse, JNI, C, Tomcat, Oracle, SQL Developer, PL/SQL, UML, RMI

IBM Solutions Delivery [August 2006 – June 2007]

Sr Java/J2EE Consultant

Senior consultant responsible for enhancement and maintenance of a web application developed for Michelin that is used for their tire technology and manufacturing

- Developed semi-finish tire process module
- Developed automated unit tests and test documents
- Performed peer testing and system testing
- Created detailed level design documentation for Green OM, SMPP and CXG tire process modules which included UML diagrams

Acquired Skills/Tools Used:

 J2EE, Xnet-Struts, Websphere Application Server, Websphere Studio Application, Developer 6.0, Oracle, Toad, Junit, SQL, Castor JDO, UML, Swing, Javascript

Rendition Digital Inc [August 2005 – August 2006]

Java Software Engineer

Member of core product team that develops the booking platform engine for the client, Datalex.

- Developed product change requests and problem requests
- Created analysis documents for change requests and problem requests
- Coordinated with the support team, customers, business analysts, and development teams
- Created automated unit tests, tests scripts, and supporting documents
- Conducted a peer code review for every project release
- Maintained and supported 12 existing booking airline projects

Project: Datalex Travel Distribution Platform

Datalex is a provider of travel distribution solutions for the global travel industry. Its clients include major airlines, hotel and resort groups, and major travel distribution organizations. It has a worldwide presence across North America, Europe, and Asia.

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

 J2EE, J2SE, Weblogic, Junit, Eclipse, Castor Mapping, XML, XML Spy

Fujitsu Philippines, Inc. [February 2005 – August 2005]

IT Consultant

Java consultant responsible for enhancement and maintenance for the project, Information Management System (PIMS). PIMS is an integrated system that serves as an analysis tool and daily time accounting for division, department, and project managers.

- Developed the modules for project enrollment and management of project tracks and phases
- Maintained and migrated existing data to a new database
- Created testing documents
- Designed a database connection using DAO pattern for the project
- Created object relational mappings for database tables using Hibernate and MiddleGen

Acquired Skills/Tools Used

• J2EE, J2SE, Oracle, Hibernate, Struts, JSTL, AJAX, Jboss, Solaris, Javascript, Jasper Reports, Dreamweaver

Galaxy Internet, Inc. (February 2004 – February 2005)

Java Developer / Team Lead

Java developer responsible for the evolution of the project. Promoted as team lead as project progresses.

- Re-engineered and refactored existing code
- Developed features regarding SMS (mobile to email, mobile to instant messenger, mobile to mobile, and vice versa) on both client and server sides
- Developed the accounting side of the project
- Tested, debugged, and maintained the project
- Supported our client on technical matters
- Mentored and delegated tasks to team members
- Trained new developers for the technologies used in the project

Client: Radiowealth Finance Company

A finance company whose primary purpose is to engage in consumer and retail lending by providing accessible credit to livelihood projects and to the micro-enterprise sector

Project: Batch Text

Project: Open-Text

A unified SMS-Instant messenger

Project: Tele-Text

An automated telephone directory assistant

Acquired Skills/Tools Used:

• MySQL, J2SE, Java Comm API, JDBC, SOCKETS, IntelliJ, Sockets, Visual C++, Java, JNI, TAPI, Visual Studio